<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-kuhn-tsvwg-careful-resume-02"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <!-- category values: std, bcp, info, exp, and historic
ipr values: full3667, noModification3667, noDerivatives3667
you can add the attributes updates="NNNN" and obsoletes="NNNN"
they will automatically be output with "(if approved)" -->

  <!-- ***** FRONT MATTER ***** -->

  <front>
    <!-- The abbreviated title is used in the page header - it is only necessary if the
full title is longer than 39 characters -->

    <title abbrev="Careful congestion control convergence">Careful convergence of congestion 
    control from retained state</title>

    <author fullname="Nicolas Kuhn" initials="N" surname="Kuhn">
      <organization>Thales Alenia Space</organization>

      <address>
        <email>nicolas.kuhn.ietf@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Emile Stephan" initials="E" surname="Stephan">
      <organization>Orange</organization>

      <address>
        <email>emile.stephan@orange.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Godred Fairhurst" initials="G" surname="Fairhurst">
      <organization>University of Aberdeen</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Department of Engineering</street>

          <street>Fraser Noble Building</street>

          <city>Aberdeen</city>

          <code>AB24 3UE</code>

          <country>Scotland, UK</country>
        </postal>

        <email>gorry@erg.abdn.ac.uk</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Christian Huitema" initials="C" surname="Huitema">
      <organization>Private Octopus Inc.</organization>

      <address>
        <email>huitema@huitema.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date year="2023" />

    <!-- If the month and year are both specified and are the current ones, xml2rfc will fill
in the current day for you. If only the current year is specified, xml2rfc will fill
in the current day and month for you. If the year is not the current one, it is
necessary to specify at least a month (xml2rfc assumes day="1" if not specified for the
purpose of calculating the expiry date).  With drafts it is normally sufficient to
specify just the year. -->

    <!-- Meta-data Declarations -->

    <area>Transport</area>

    <workgroup>Internet Engineering Task Force</workgroup>

    <!-- WG name at the upperleft corner of the doc,
IETF is fine for individual submissions.
If this element is not present, the default is "Network Working Group",
which is used by the RFC Editor as a nod to the history of the IETF. -->

    <keyword>congestion control, convergence, QUIC</keyword>

    <!-- Keywords will be incorporated into HTML output
files in a meta tag but they have no effect on text or nroff
output. If you submit your draft to the RFC Editor, the
keywords will be used for the search engine. -->

    <abstract>
      <t>This document specifies careful convergence of 
      Congestion Control (CC), providing
      a cautious method that enables fast startup for a wide
      range of connections or reconnections.</t>
      <t>The method reuses a set of computed CC parameters that
      are based on the previously observed path characteristics between
      the same pair of transport endpoints, such as the
      bottleneck bandwidth, available capacity, or the RTT. These parameters
      are stored, allowing them to be later used to modify the CC behavior
      of a subsequent connection. The document also discusses assumptions
      and defines requirements around how a
      sender utilizes these parameters to provide opportunities for a
      connection to more quickly get up to speed (i.e. utilize the available
      capacity). It discusses how these changes impact the capacity at a
      shared network bottleneck and the safe response that is needed after any
      indication that the new rate is inappropriate. The method is expected to be appropriate to IETF transports.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="sec:introduction" title="Introduction">
      
	<t>All Internet transports are required to either use a CC method, or
	to constrain their rate of transmission <xref target="RFC8085"></xref>. In 2010, 
	a survey of alternative CC methods <xref target="RFC5783"></xref>, noted that there
	are challenges when a CC operates across an Internet path with a high and/or
	variable bandwidth-delay product (BDP), this mechanisms targets this challenge.</t>
      
      	<t>A CC method typically takes time to ramp-up the packet rate,
      	called the "slow-start phase", informally known as the time to "Get up
      	to speed". This slow start phase is a period in which a sender
      	intentionally uses less capacity than might be available, with the
      	intention to avoid or limit overshooting the actual capacity at a bottleneck.
      	This can result in increased queuing (latency/jitter) and/or
      	congestion packet loss to the flow. Any overshoot in the capacity can also have a
      	detrimental effect on other flows sharing a common bottleneck. In the
      	extreme case, persistent congestion could result in unwanted starvation of
      	other flows <xref target="RFC8867"></xref> (i.e., Preventing other flows
		from successfully sharing a common bottleneck).</t>
	    
      <t>The method can improve performance by 
      reducing the time to get up to speed, and hence can reduce the
      total duration of a transfer.  
      It introduces an alternative method to select initial CC parameters,
       including a way to more rapidly and safely grow the congestion
       window (cwnd).
       This method is based on temporal sharing (sometimes known as
       caching) of a set of computed CC parameters that relate to a previously 
       observed path, such as the bottleneck
       bandwidth, available capacity, and RTT. These
       parameters are stored and used to modify the CC
       behaviour of a subsequent connection between the same local and remote endpoints.</t>

	<t>When used with the QUIC transport, it provides transport services that resemble 
	those currently available in TCP, such as TCP Control Block (TCB) <xref target="RFC9040"></xref> caching or
        updates to support application-limited traffic.</t>

        <section title="Using the Information with Care">
	<t>"Generally, implementations are advised
      	to be cautious when using previous values on a new path", as stated in <xref
      	target="RFC9000"></xref>. This advice is appropriate for any IETF transport protocol.</t>

	<t>Care is therefore needed in the use of any temporal information
 	to assure safe use of the Internet and to be robust to changes
 	in traffic patterns, network routing and link/node failures.
 	There are also cases where using the parameters of a previous
        connection are not appropriate, and a need to evaluate the potential
		for malicious use of the method.</t>
		
      	</section>  <!-- end of use with care --> 
          
	<section title="Receiver Preference">
		
	     <t>Whilst a sender could take optimization decisions without considering 
      	     the receiver's preference, there are cases where a client at the receiver
             could have information that 
             is not available at the sender. In these cases, a client 
             could explicitely ask for tuning the 
             slow start when the application continues transmission, or to to inhibit tuning. 
             Examples where this could have benefit include:
             <list style="numbers">
 		<t>when a receiver understands that the pattern of traffic that a connection will use is different
			(e.g., the volume of data to be sent, the length of the session, or the maximum transfer rate required);</t>
 		<t>when a receiver has a local indication that the path/local interface has changed since CC parameters were stored;</t>
 		<t>when there is information related to the current hardware limitations at the receiver;</t>
      		<t>where the receiver understands the capacity that will be needed for other concurrent flows 
		that might be expected to share the capacity of the path.</t>
	</list></t>
			
 		<t>A related document complements this CC method by allowing 
		the sender-generated transport information to be stored at the receiver
		<xref target="I-D.kuhn-quic-bdpframe-extension"></xref>. 
		This 
      	    	enables a receiver to implement a policy that informs a sender
      	    	whether the receiver desires the sender to reuse the CC parameters.
		By transfering the information to a receiver, it also releases the
		sender from needing to retain CC parameter state for each
		receiver. </t>
	</section> <!-- end of Receiver Preference -->

	<section anchor="sec-use_case" title="Examples of Scenarios of Interest">
    
    	        <t> This section provides a set of examples where the method is expected to improve performance.</t>
		
	        <t>
		The method is expected to have benefit when a transfer
       		sendd significantly more data than allowed by the IW, 
	        and the BDP is also significantly 
		more than the IW.</t>
		
		<t>An application could use a series of connections over the
           	same path (i.e. resumes a connection to the same endpoint). 
		This can be used by a sender that performs a unidirectional data transfer
        	towards the receiver, (e.g., a receiver downloading a file or a web page). 
		Without the method, 
		each connection would otherwise need to individually 
		discover the CC parameters.</t>

		<t>Either or both endpoints can assume the role of a
        	sender or a receiver. The method supports a bidirectional data transfer,
		where both endpoints simultaneously send data to
       		each other (e.g., remote execution of an application, or a
        	bidirectional video conference call).</t>
		
		<t>Examples where temporal sharing of CC parameters 
 		can eliminate round-trip times at the start of a new connection
 		include the following: 
		
		 <section title="A Mobility example"> 
	
      		<t>In this example, an application resumes using capacity after a pause 
		in transmission. Without the method, the application that
           	pauses would otherwise need to discover new CC parameters 
		each time it connects to the same endpoint.</t>      
		<t>A varient of this exmaple is when the application reconnects after a disruption that
		had temporarily reduced the path
           	capacity (e.g., after to a link propagation
           	impairment, or  where a user on a train journey travels through
	 	different areas of connectivity) before the endpoint
		returns to use a path with the original characteristics.</t>
	    </section><!-- End of intro:examples:simple -->

	    <section title="A Satellite Access Network Example using QUIC"> 
		<t> QUIC introduces the concept of transport parameters (Section 4 of
        	<xref target="RFC9000"></xref>). The present document
		adds to this by noting that a new
        	connection can utilize a set of key transport parameters from a
			previous connection to reduce the completion time for a transfer.</t>
		    
        	<t>This benefit is particularly
        	evident for a path where the RTT is much larger than for typical
        	Internet paths. In a specific example of high BDP path, a satellite access network,
		takes up to 9 seconds to complete a 5.3 MB transfer
		using standard CC, whereas using the
        	specified method the transfer time could reduce to 4 seconds <xref
        	target="IJSCN"></xref>; and the time to complete a 1 MB transfer could
        	be reduced by 62 % <xref target="MAPRG111"></xref>. Benefit is also
        	expected for other sizes of transfer and for different path
        	characteristics that also result in a path with high BDP.</t>
	    </section> <!-- End of intro:examples:satcom -->
	    
	    <section title="Another Network Example"> 
		    <t>{XXX-Editor note: A future revision can provide further Path Examples here.}</t>
	    </section> <!-- End of intro:examples:other -->

    </section> <!--- end of examples -->
   
</section> <!-- end of introduction and motivation -->

<!-- ************************************ -->
<!-- The protocol spec follows below here -->

<section anchor="notation" title="Language, notations and terms">

      <t>This section provides a brief summary of key terms and the
      requirements language that is used.</t>

    <section anchor="sec:req_language" title="Requirements Language">
        <t>The keywords "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
        "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
        "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in BCP
        14 <xref target="RFC2119"></xref> <xref target="RFC8174"></xref> when,
        and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.</t>
    </section>

    <section title="Use of CC Information collected by the Sender">
	<t>Sender-generated information is used in this document for two functions:
	<list>
		<t>Information to characterize the saved path, to allow a sender to
		establish if the saved information indicates the saved path 
		is consistent with the current path.</t>
	 	<t>Information about the capacity that was available on a saved path, 
		to allow a later sender to
	 	determine an appropriate set of CC parameters for its current path.</t>
	</list></t>
    </section> <!--- End of Notation: the information -->

    <section anchor="sec-terms_def" title="Notations and Terms">
        <t> The document uses language drawn
      from a range of IETF RFCs.  It defines current, and saved values for a set of CC
        parameters:
	<list style="symbols">

<!-- GF (Feb 2023): Removed the IW from this information block??? -->
<!-- it could potentially be in BDP but is not needed here -->
<!--	<t>IW: Initial Window <xref target="RFC9002"></xref>;</t> -->
<!--            <t>current_iw: Current IW;</t> -->
<!--            <t>recom_iw: Recommended IW;</t> -->

            <t>current_bb : The current estimated bottleneck bandwidth;</t>

            <t>saved_bb: The estimated bottleneck bandwidth preserved from a
            previous connection;</t>

            <t>current_rtt: The current RTT;</t>

            <t>saved_rtt: The measured RTT, preserved from a previous
            connection;</t>

            <t>endpoint_token: The Endpoint Token of the receiver;</t>

            <t>current_endpoint_token: The current Endpoint Token of the receiver;</t>

            <t>saved_endpoint_token: The Endpoint Token of a previous connection by the
            receiver;</t>

            <t>remembered BDP parameters: A combination of the saved_rtt and
            saved_bb.</t>
          </list>
	</t>

        <t>The Endpoint Token is described in <xref target="endpoint_token"></xref>.
	</t>

      </section> <!-- End of Notation: end of terms -->
</section><!-- End of Notation -->

<section anchor="sec-phase" title="The Phases of CC using Careful Resume">
      <t>This section defines a series of phases that the
      CC algorithm moves through as a connection gets up to speed
      when it uses the Careful Resume method. 
      
      <!--- GF: Changed to subsections to match next section format -->
      
	<section title="Observe Phase:">   
          <t>During a previous connection, information about the specific path
	  to an endpoint is saved. This is used to characterise the path and
	  to indicate the capacity that was available. It includes the current RTT
          (current_rtt), bottleneck bandwidth (current_bb) and current receiver
          Endpoint Token (current_endpoint_token) stored as saved_rtt, saved_bb and
          saved_endpoint_token <xref target="sec-measure"></xref>.</t>
	 </section> <!--- title="Observe Phase:"--->   
	      
	 <section title="Reconnaissance Phase:">   
          <t> When a sender resumes between the same pair of endpoints, 
	  (aka the same path) it enters the Reconnaissance Phase.
	  The sender only enters this phase when there are saved CC parameters for the same
	  pair of endpoints and this information is currently valid (i.e., the parameters have
	  not expired.)
	  When a method is provided (such as the BDP_Frame), a receiver can request
	  the sender to not enter this phase.</t>
	  
	  <t>In the Reconnaissance Phase, the sender sends initial data, limited by the Initial Window.
          This 
	  phase checks whether the current path is consistent with the saved path information.
	  The sender measures the path characteristics of the present
          path to confirm that the path is consistent with the previously characterised path
          (including a similar RTT) <xref target="sec-recon"></xref>.
	  <list>
	  	<t>If the sender determines that the path RTT or the other saved path information
	 	 are not consistent with the current path, 
		then the sender continues using the standard CC, and enters 
		the Normal Phase.</t>
		 <t>To ensure a sender avoids resuming under severely congested conditions,
	         if any sent initial data 
	  	 was not correctly received, the sender continues using the standard CC, and enters 
		 the Normal Phase.</t> 
	 	<t>If the sender confirms both that the saved and current path information are consistent 
		and that the sent initial data 
	  	was correctly received, the sender enters the Unvalidated Phase.</t>
	  </list>
	  </t>
	 </section> <!--- title="Reconnaissance Phase:"--->   
	      
	 <section title="Unvalidated Phase:">   
          <t>In the Unvalidated Phase, a sender can
	  utilize the saved path information to update its CC parameters. 
          This phase allows a
          rate higher than allowed by a traditional
          slow-start mechanism. The convergence towards the
          previous rate is expected to be faster, but should not be instantaneous, to avoid
          adding congestion to an already congested bottleneck. In this phase, the sender
	  continues to check the saved and current path information are consistent <xref target="sec-unvalid"></xref>. 
	  <list style="numbers">
              <t>If a sender determines either that previous parameters
              are not valid (due to a detected change in the path) or congestion was experienced,
              then the sender needs to enter the Retreat Phase (see below).</t>
	       <t>If acknowledgments show that the unvalidated rate was succesfully used 
	       without inducing significant congestion to the path, 
	       then the sender is permitted to continue at the rate used in 
	       in the unvalidated phase when it continues in the Normal Phase.</t>
            </list></t>
	 </section> <!--- title="Unvalidated Phase:"--->   
	      
	 <section title="Retreat Phase:">   
          <t>In the Retreat Phase, the sender stops using the saved CC parameters. 
	  This phase is designed to mitigate the impact on other
	  flows that might have been sharing a congested bottleneck when in the Unvalidated Phase. 
	  The sender needs to re-initialise CC parameters to drain any queue that has built
	  at the bottleneck during the Unvalidated Phase and allow other flows to then regain
	  their share of the available capacity. This reaction differs to a traditional
	  CC reaction to congestion, because in this case the capacity estimate was unvalidated <xref target="sec-retreat"></xref>.
	  Saved CC parameters for this path should be removed from any cache, to prevent the
	  parameters being used again with other flows.</t>
	  
	  <t>When the sender transitions to the Safe Retreat Phase, there may still be packets 
	  that were sent in the Unvalidated Phase that have not yet been acknowledged. 
	  If these packets from the Unvalidated Phase are declared lost,
	  they do not trigger an additional CC reaction.</t>
	  
	 <t> If the data in the packets that are lost in the Unvalidated Phase needs to be recovered,
	 this recovery commences using the reduced window set on entry to the Safe Retreat Phase. 
	 In the case of multiple loss, this could require multiple RTTs to complete 
	 successful resending of data that lost in the Unvalidated Phase. 
	 The loss of the packets used to resend data is considered a separate congestion event, 
	 and this does also trigger another CC reaction.
	  <list style="numbers">
              <t>The sender then enters the Normal phase with re-initialised CC parameters.</t>
          </list></t>
	 </section> <!--- title="Retreat Phase:"--->   
	      
	 <section title="Normal Phase:">   

          <t>The sender resumes using the normal CC method.</t>
	  <t>If the sender experiences an Retransmission Time Out (RTO) expiry, the sender returns to the normal CC phase and processes the RTO expiry.</t>   
        </list></t>

</section> <!-- End of Phases -->

<section title="Congestion Control Guidelines and Requirements">	
	
    <t>The sender is limited by any rate-limitation of the transport
    protocol being used. For QUIC this includes: flow control mechanisms or amplification
    attack prevention. In particular, a QUIC receiver might need to issue proactive
    MAX_DATA frames to increase the flow control limits of a connection
    that is started with this method to gain the expected benefit.</t>
		
    <!-- The maximum number of packets that can be sent without
    acknowledgments needs to be chosen to avoid the creation and the
    increase of congestion for the path. -->
		
    <section anchor="sec-measure" title="Determining the current Path Capacity in the Observe Phase">
			
	<t>Congestion controllers, such as CUBIC or RENO, can estimate the
        saved_bb and current_bb values by utilizing a combination of the
        cwnd/flight_size and the minimum RTT. A different method could be used
        to estimate the same values when using a rate-based congestion
        controller, such as BBR <xref target="I-D.cardwell-iccrg-bbr-congestion-control"></xref>.
	   
	<list style="symbols">
          	<t>Observe Phase: The sender SHOULD NOT store and/or send CC parameter
          	information related to an estimated bottleneck bandwidth
          	(saved_bb) (see <xref target="sec-terms_def"></xref> for more
          	details on bottleneck bandwidth definition), if the cwnd is not at
		least four times larger than the IW.</t>
		
          	<t>Observe Phase: The sender SHOULD update the stored CC parameters and/or send updated CC parameter
          	information related to an estimated bottleneck bandwidth
          	(saved_bb) (see <xref target="sec-terms_def"></xref> for more
          	details on bottleneck bandwidth definition), if there are significant changes in the CC parameters 
		that the session has measured. The rate of the updates transmission SHOULD be limited to at most
		one update for several RTTs of time.</t>
		<t>Observe Phase: There are cases where the current cwnd
            	does not reflect the bottleneck bandwidth. At the end of the CC slow
           	start phase, the value of cwnd can be significantly larger than
            	the minimum value needed to utilize the path (i.e., a cwnd
           	overshoot). In most case, the cwnd finally converges to a stable
            	value after several more RTTs. It would be inappropriate to use an
            	overshoot in the cwnd as a basis for estimating the bottleneck
            	bandwidth. NOTE: One mitigation could be to further restrict to
            	only a fraction (e.g., 1/2) of the previously used cwnd; another
            	mitigation might be to calculate the bottleneck bandwidth based on
            	the flight_size or an averaged cwnd.</t>

	</list></t>
	    
    </section> <!-- Observe Phase  (measure) -->

    <section anchor="sec-recon"  title="Confirming the Path in the Reconnaissance Phase">
	
	<t>The sender sends initial data limited by the IW - this value is
        assumed a safe starting point for any path where there is no path
        information or congestion control information. This limit avoids
        adding excessive congestion to a potentially congested path.</t>

        <t>The sender monitors the reception of the initial data. If the path
        characteristics resemble those of a previously observed connection 
	(i.e., current_rtt &lt; 1.2*saved_rtt) and
        all data was acknowledged without reported congestion, the
        method permits the sender to utilize the saved_bb as an input to
		adapt current_bb to rapidly determine a new safe rate.</t>
	<t>    
	<list style="symbols">
	<t>Reconnaissance Phase: A snder MUST limit the initial data,
	sent in the first RTT of transmitted data, 
	to not more than the
        IW <xref target="RFC9000"></xref>.</t>
	</list></t>
	    
	<t>When used in a controlled
        network, additional information about local path characteristics
        could be known, which might be used to configure a non-standard
        IW.</t>
 
    <section anchor="sec-confirm" title="Confirming the Path">
	 <t>Paths can change with respect to time for many reasons.
	This could result in previously measured CC parameters
        becoming irrelevant.
	    
	<list style="symbols">
	 <t>Endpoint Token change: If the Endpoint Token changes 
            	(i.e., the saved_endpoint_token is different from the
            	current_endpoint_token), the different Endpoint Token can be assumed as an
            	indication of a different network path. This new path does not
	    	necessarily exhibit the same characteristics as the old one.</t>

         <t>RTT change: A significant change in RTT is regarded as an indication
         that the network conditions have changed. Since the CC information
         is directly impacted by the RTT, a significant change in the RTT
         is a strong indication that the previously estimated BDP
	 parameters are likely to not be valid for the current path.</t>

	<t>Lifetime of the information: The CC information is temporal.
        Frequent connections to the same endpoint are likely to track
	changes, but long-term use of previous values is not appropriate.</t>
           
	</list></t>

	<t>{NOTE: A future revision of this document needs to specify how long
	CC Parameters can be cached, possibly based on TCP-new-CWV or TCB}.

	<list style="symbols">
        <t>Reconnaissance Phase: The sender MUST compare the measured
        transport parameters (in particular current_rtt) of the new session
        with those of the previous session (in particular
        saved_rtt). The method MUST NOT be used when the path fails to be
        validated.</t>
	<t>Reconnaissance Phase: The sender MUST NOT use the parameters unless
        the first IW packets when packets are detected as lost or
         acknowledgments indicate the packets were ECN CE-marked. These are
         indication of potential congestion and therefore the method MUST NOT
         be used; </t>

	</list></t>
	    
	<t>{XXX-Editor-note: RTT check should be a range rather than an
      	inequality (current_rtt &lt; 1.2*saved_rtt).}</t>
	
    	</section>	
   </section> <!--- Reconnaissance -->

    <section anchor="sec-unvalid" title="Safety Requirements for the Unvalidated Phase">
	<t> This section defines the safety requirements
	for using saved CC parameters to update the cwnd.
	These safety guidelines are designed to mitigate the risk that sender
      	adds excessive congestion to an already congested path. </t>
		
	<t>{XXX-Editor note: The sender ought not to re-utilize all the capacity it previously
        used, to avoid starving other flows that started or increased their capacity after the last measurement.
       	How strong should this be stated: ... MUST or SHOULD ... What safety
        factor is appropriate for the resuming sender? If using slow-start it
       	would anyway double the rate on the next RTT, so is capacity*2/3
        appropriate to initially try?} </t>
		
	<t>The method needs to be designed to avoid sending
        excessive data into a congested bottleneck, because this can have
        a material impact on any flows sharing that bottleneck, and the
	ability of those flows to control their own sending rate.
		
	<list style="symbols">
	<t>Unvalidated Phase: A new connection MUST NOT directly use the previously measured saved_rtt and
        saved_bb to simply initialize a new flow to resume sending at the same
       	rate. The method needs to set cwnd less than or equal to 2/3 the previous value</t>
	</list></t>
	
	<t>{NOTE:
        A later revision needs to define how to decide a significant change.}</t>
				
      	<section title="Exit for the Unvalidated Phase because of Variable Network Conditions">
 		<t>The network conditions for the same path can also change over time.
	        Bottleneck bandwidth and network traffic can
            	change at any time. An Internet method needs to be robust to
            	network conditions that can differ from one connection to the next,
            	due to variations in the forwarding path, reconfiguration of
            	equipment or changes in the link conditions.
	
		<list style="symbols">
		
		<t>Unvalidated Phase: Careful Resume MUST be robust to changes in network traffic, including the
            	arrival of new traffic flows that compete for the bottleneck
		capacity.</t>
            	<t>Unvalidated Phase: Preventing Starvation of New Flows. It would not be appropriate
            	to fully use a bottleneck bandwidth estimate based on a previous
            	measurement of capacity, because new flows might have started
           	using the available capacity since that measurement was made. The
            	mitigation could be to restrict to only a fraction (e.g., 1/2) of
            	the previously used cwnd. The primary mitigation is to perform a

          	<t>Unvalidated phase: The sender MUST transition to the Retreat Phase
          	when packets are detected as lost or acknowledgments indicate the
          	packets were ECN CE-marked. These are indication of potential
          	congestion and therefore the method is not used.</t>
		</list></t>

    	</section> <!-- End of Safety: Network Conditions -->
			
	<section anchor="sec-pace" title="Pacing in the Unvalidated Phase">
		<t> The sender needs to avoid sending a burst of packets as a result of a
              	step-increase in the congestion window <xref target="RFC8085"></xref>,
              	<xref target="RFC9000"></xref>. 
		Various modifications to the sender to avoid line-rate bursts have been 
		suggested (e.g., <xref target="I-D.hughes-restart"></xref>). 
		acing the packets as a function of
              	the current_rtt can provide this additional safety during the
              	unvalidated period.</t>

          	<t>Identify a relevant pacing rhythm:
		<list style="symbols">
              		<t>The sender estimates a pacing rhythm using saved_rtt and
             		 saved_bb. The Inter-packet Transmission Time (ITT) is determined
              		from the ratio between the current Maximum Message Size (MMS) and
              		the ratio between the saved_bb and saved_rtt. A tunable safety
              		margin can avoid sending more than a recommended maximum IW
              		(recom_iw): 
			<list style="symbols">
                  		<t>current_iw = min(recom_iw,saved_bb)</t>
                  		<t>ITT = MSS/(current_iw/saved_rtt)</t>
                	</list></t>
            	</list></t>

      	    <t>This follows the idea presented in <xref target="RFC4782"></xref>,
      	    <xref target="I-D.irtf-iccrg-sallantin-initial-spreading"></xref> and
      	    <xref target="CONEXT15"></xref>.</t>	
	</section> <!-- Pacing in Careful Resume -->
    </section> <!-- Unvalidated Phase -->

   <section anchor="sec-retreat" title="Safety Requirements for the Retreat Phase">
	<t>This section defines the safety requirements
        after a path change or congestion has been detected during the Unvalidated Phase.</t>

	<t>The transport parameters are adjusted in the Unvalidated Phase, resulting in a higher cwnd.
	If there are indications of congestion, this also indicates that the parameters
	no longer reflect the current path, and the cwnd must be reduced to avoid
	overshoot of the bottleneck
      	capacity. This can result from changes in traffic at the bootleneck and/or
	changes in the path capacity.</t> 
	    
	<t>{XXX-Editor note: A later revision will guide on the mitigation after detected congestion.}</t>

         </section> <!-- End of Safety: Network Conditions- Mitigating Mistakes -->
  </section><!-- Safety Requirements for the Retreat Phase -->
		
  <section anchor="sec-normal" title="Returning to Normal Congestion Control">
	<t>The CC controller returns to the Normal Phase.
	  
	<list style="symbols">
	    <t>For NewReno and CUBIC, it is recommended to exit slow-start
            and enter the congestion avoidance phase.</t>

            <t>For BBR CC, it is recommended to enter the "probe bandwidth"
            state.</t>
    </list></t>
	<t>{XXX-Editor note: A later revision will guide on the entering normal CC.}</t>

   </section><!-- End of normal-->	

</section> <!--  Guidelines -->	  

<section anchor="sec-acknowledgments" title="Acknowledgments">
      <t>The authors would like to thank John Border, Gabriel Montenegro, Patrick McManus,
      Ian Swett, Igor Lubashev, Robin Marx, Roland Bless and Franklin Simo for
      their fruitful comments on earlier versions of this document.</t>
      <t>The authors would like to particularly thank Tom Jones for co-authoring 
      previous versions of this document.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="sec-IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>{XXX-Editor note: Text is required to register any IANA Considerations.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="sec-security" title="Security Considerations">

	<t>This document does not exhibit specific security considerations since only sender level considerations are proposed. Security considerations for the interactions with the receiver are discussed in <xref
      target="I-D.kuhn-quic-bdpframe-extension"></xref>.</t>

    </section> <!-- Sec Considerations -->
	    
  </middle>

  <!--  BACK MATTER -->

  <back>
    <!-- References split into informative and normative -->

    <!-- There are 2 ways to insert reference entries from the citation libraries:
1. define an ENTITY at the top, and use "ampersand character"RFC2629; here (as shown)
2. simply use a PI "less than character"?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119.xml"?> here
(for I-Ds: include="reference.I-D.narten-iana-considerations-rfc2434bis.xml")
Both are cited textually in the same manner: by using xref elements.
If you use the PI option, xml2rfc will, by default, try to find included files in the same
directory as the including file. You can also define the XML_LIBRARY environment variable
with a value containing a set of directories to search.  These can be either in the local
filing system or remote ones accessed by http (http://domain/dir/... ).-->

    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119.xml"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4782.xml"?>

      <!-- <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6349.xml"?> -->

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8085.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8174.xml"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8801.xml"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.9000.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.9040.xml"?>

      <!-- <?rfc include="reference.RFC.9001.xml"?> -->

    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      	<?rfc include="reference.I-D.irtf-iccrg-sallantin-initial-spreading.xml"?>
      	<?rfc include="reference.I-D.hughes-restart.xml"?>
	<?rfc include="reference.I-D.cardwell-iccrg-bbr-congestion-control.xml"?>
      	<?rfc include="reference.I-D.kuhn-quic-bdpframe-extension.xml"?>
	    
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5783.xml"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8867.xml"?>
      
      <reference anchor="MAPRG111">
        <front>
          <title>Feedback from using QUIC's 0-RTT-BDP extension over SATCOM
          public access</title>

          <author initials="N" surname="Kuhn"></author>

          <author initials="E" surname="Stephan"></author>

          <author initials="G" surname="Fairhurst"></author>

          <author initials="T" surname="Jones"></author>

          <author initials="C" surname="Huitema"></author>

          <date year="2022" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="IETF 111 - MAPRG meeting" value="" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="IJSCN">
        <front>
          <title>Google QUIC performance over a public SATCOM access</title>

          <author initials="L" surname="Thomas"></author>

          <author initials="E" surname="Dubois"></author>

          <author initials="N" surname="Kuhn"></author>

          <author initials="E" surname="Lochin"></author>

          <date year="2019" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="International Journal of Satellite Communications and Networking"
                    value="10.1002/sat.1301" />
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="CONEXT15">
        <front>
          <title>Halfback: Running Short Flows Quickly and Safely</title>

          <author initials="Q" surname="Li"></author>

          <author initials="M" surname="Dong"></author>

          <author initials="P B" surname="Godfrey"></author>

          <date year="2015" />
        </front>

        <seriesInfo name="ACM CoNEXT" value="" />
      </reference>
    </references>

<section anchor="endpoint_token" title="Annexe: An Endpoint Token">

    <t>
    This proposes an Endpoint Token to allow a sender to identify its own
		    view of the network path that it is using. In <xref target="I-D.kuhn-quic-bdpframe-extension"></xref>
	    this Endpoint Tokencould be shared and used as an
    opaque path identifier to other parties and the sender can verify if
    this is one of its current paths.
    </t>

    <section title="Creating an Endpoint Token">
        <t>
        When computing the Endpoint Token, the sender includes information to identify
        the path on which it sends, for example:
        <list style="symbols">
	    <t>
            it must include a unique identifier for itself (e.g., a globally
            assigned address/prefix; or randomly chosen value).
	    </t>
	    <t>
            it must include an identifier for the destination (e.g., a
            destination IP address or name).
	    </t>
	    <t>
            it must include an interface identifier (e.g., an index value or a MAC address to associate the
            endpoint with the interface on which the path starts);
	    </t>
	    <t>
            it could include other information such as the DSCP, ports, flow
            label, etc (recognising that this additional infromation might improve the path
            differentiation, but that this can can reduce the re-usability of the
            token);
	    </t>
	    <t>
            it could include any other information the sender chooses to
	    include, and potentially including PvD information <xref target="RFC8801"></xref> or
            information relating to its public-facing IP address;
	    </t>
	    <t>
            it could include a nonce;
	    </t>
	    <t>
            it could include a time-dependent value to define the validity
            period of the token.
	    </t>
       </list></t> 

        <t>
        When creating an Endpoint Token, the sender has to ensure the following:
        <list style="numbers">
	    <t>
            To reduce the likelihood of misuse of the Endpoint Token, the value
            should be encoded in a way that hides the component information
	    from the recipient and any eavesdropper on the path.
            </t>
	    <t>
            The sender can recalculate the Endpoint Token if it needs to validate a
            previously issued token; and that the Endpoint Token itself can be
            included in the computed integrity check for any path
            information it provides.
	    </t>
	    <t>
            The Endpoint Token is designed so that if shared, it prevents another party from deriving
            private data from the token, or to use the token to perform
            unwanted likability with other information. This implies that
            the Endpoint Token MUST necessarily be different when used to identify
            paths using different interfaces.
            </t>
       </list> </t>
    </section>

 </section> <!-- End of An Endpoint Token -->
	  
<section title="Summary">

          <figure anchor="fig-summary" title="Comparing Careful Resume solutions">
            <artwork><![CDATA[
+---------+-----------+----------------+---------------+-----------+
|Rationale| Solution  |    Advantage   |    Drawback   |  Comment  |
+---------+-----------+----------------+---------------+-----------+
|#1       |#1         |                |               |           |
|Variable |set        |Ingress optim.  |Risk of adding |MUST NOT   |
|Network  |current_*  |                | congestion    |implement  |
|         |to saved_* |                |               |           |
|         +-----------+----------------+---------------+-----------+
|         |#2         |                |               |           |
|         |Implement  |Reduce risk of  |Negative impact|MUST       |
|         |safety     | adding         | on ingress    |implement  |
|         |check      | congestion     | optim.        |Section 3  |
+---------+-----------+----------------+---------------+-----------+


]]></artwork>
</figure>
	
<!-- text relating to BDP Frame moved out of this draft -->
		
</section> <!-- end of Summary -->
</back>
</rfc>

			
